Guide to the Thomas Whiteside papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I: Writings, 1839-1991
  - Subseries I.1: Published Articles and Books, 1839-1995
    - The Investigation of Ralph Nader: General Motors vs. One Determined Man (book)
      - Research Files
        - Moynihan, Daniel, 1971 (Box 12)
        - Notes, 1972 (Box 12)
    - "The Long Sweep"--Typescript, 1951 (Box 12)
    - "The Man from the Iron City"
      - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 12)
      - Galleys/Proofs, 1969 (Box 22)
      - The Man from the Iron City: Scenes of a Promotional Age (book proposal), 1987, (2 folders) (Box 22)
      - Research Files
        - Audiocassettes, undated (1 tape) (Box 24e)
        - Notebooks, 1968, undated, (5 folders) (Box 12)
        - Notes, 1968-1969, undated, (3 folders) (Box 12)
      - Typescript, 1969, (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - The New Republic/The Reporter--Scrapbook of Articles, 1947-1950 (Box 12)
    - "No Lobster Men from Neptune"--Correspondence, 1954 (Box 12)
    - "Oh the Head!"
      - Draft, undated (Box 12)
      - Galleys/Proofs, 1966 (Box 12)
      - Research Files--1962-1966 (Box 12)
    - "The One Ton Pencil"--Research Files--Notes, undated, (4 folders) (Box 12)
    - "The Pink Chrysanthemum Trail"--Typescript/Draft, 1967, (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - "A Powerful Sense of His Duty"
      - Alone through the Dark Sea (book)--Galleys/Proofs, undated (Box 28)
      - Correspondence
        - 1958 (Box 13)
        - Letters to Carlsen, 1952 (Box 13)
      - Galleys/Proofs, 1958 (Box 23)
      - Research Files
        - 1946-1957, undated, (12 folders) (Box 13)
        - Award Ceremonies, 1952 (Box 13)
        - Clippings, 1952-1954, undated (Box 13)
        - Notes, 1952-1954, undated, (3 folders) (Box 13)
        - Reel-to-Reel Audio, undated (1 reel) (Box 24)
      - Typescript, undated, (2 folders) (Box 24)
      - Typescript/Draft, undated, (2 folders) (Box 24)
    - "The Selling Season: We'll Think about it, Dave"
      - Galleys/Proofs, 1960 (Box 23)
      - Research Files--Notes, 1960, undated, (5 folders) (Box 13)
      - Typescript, 1960 (Box 13)
    - "Shaking the Network Tree"
      - Correspondence--Galbraith, John Kenneth, 1975 (Box 13)
      - Galleys/Proofs, 1974 (Box 13)
      - Galleys/Proofs, 1975 (Box 23)
      - Research Files
        - 1970-1974, (5 folders) (Box 13)
        - Nixon Resignation Speech, 1974 (Box 13)
        - Notebooks, undated, (3 folders) (Box 13)
        - Notes, 1974, (3 folders) (Box 13)
        - Notes, 1974, undated, (3 folders) (Box 14)
        - Public Television, 1971-1973 (Box 14)
        - White House and Electronic Media, 1974, undated (Box 14)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 14)
    - "The Soap Conflict"
      - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 14)
      - Drafts, undated (Box 14)
      - Research Files
        - Advertisements, 1962, undated (Box 14)
        - Colgate-Palmolive Company, 1964 (Box 14)
        - Continental Oil Company, 1964 (Box 14)
        - Detergent Age, 1964 (Box 14)
        - Notes, undated, (3 folders) (Box 14)
        - Ohio River Valley Water Sanitation Commission, 1964 (Box 14)
        - Redbook Magazine--Market Reports, 1958 (Box 14)
        - Soap and Detergent Association, 1964 (Box 14)
        - Soft Detergents, 1963-1964 (Box 14)
      - "The Suds Conflict"--Galleys/Proofs, 1964 (Box 14)
    - "Something Wrong with the Island"
      - Correspondence, 1962-1966 (Box 14)
      - Drawing of (for The New Yorker piece), undated (Box 14)
      - Galleys/Proofs, 1963 (Box 23)
      - Research Files--Notes, 1961, undated, (2 folders) (Box 14)
      - "Tristan"--Galleys/Proofs, 1963 (Box 23)
    - "Soviet TV"
      - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 14)
      - Galleys, 1985 (Box 14)
      - Research Files--Notes, 1985, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - "Stand-Ups"
      - Correspondence, undated (Box 14)
      - Research Files--Notebooks, 1985 (Box 14)
    - "Talk of the Town/Notes and Comment"
      - 1979 (Box 14)
      - "Decision on 2, 4, 5-T"--Typescript, 1971 (Box 14)
      - Draft, undated, (2 folders) (Box 14)
      - Galleys/Proofs, 1963, 1968, 1981, (3 folders) (Box 23)
    - "Tomatoes"
      - Correspondence, 1975-1978, 1991, (2 folders) (Box 14)
      - Financial, 1975 (Box 14)
      - Galleys/Proofs, 1975, (2 folders) (Box 14)
      - Galleys/Proofs, 1977 (Box 23)
      - Research Files
        - 1969-1975, undated, (3 folders) (Box 14)
        - Florida Tomato Committee, 1973-1974 (Box 14)
        - Growing Methods, 1973-1975 (Box 14)
        - "Hard Tomatoes", 1972 (Box 14)
        - MH-1, 1957-1974 (Box 14)
        - Mexico, 1969-1974 (Box 14)
        - Notebooks, 1975, undated, (2 folders) (Box 14)
        - Notebooks, undated, (2 folders) (Box 15)
        - Notes, 1975-1976, undated, (2 folders) (Box 15)
        - Reviews, 1977 (Box 15)
        - Typescript, 1975, undated, (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Twiggy and Justin (book)
      - Agreement Termination, 1984 (Box 15)
      - Book Reviews, 1968 (Box 15)
      - Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 15)
    - Unidentified Galley/Proof (NBC/Lunar Landing), undated (Box 15)
    - "The Wheel Man"--Typescript/Draft, undated (Box 15)
    - The Withering Rain (book)
      - Book Reviews, 1971 (Box 15)
      - Correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 15)
    - "The Yellow Rain Complex"
      - Correspondence
        - 1987-1991, (8 folders) (Box 15)
        - Weisner, Louis, 1986 (Box 15)
        - Yeltsin, Boris (outgoing), 1989 (Box 15)
      - Drafts, circa 1989, undated, (2 folders) (Box 15)
      - Drafts Part I, undated (Box 15)
      - Drafts and Galley Inserts, Part I, undated (Box 15)
      - Drafts and Galley Inserts, Part II, undated (Box 15)
      - Expenses, 1988 (Box 15)
      - Galley Inserts, 1990-1991, undated, (3 folders) (Box 15)
      - Galleys/Proofs, Part I, 1990, (4 folders) (Box 15)
      - Galleys/Proofs, Part II, 1991, undated, (3 folders) (Box 15)
      - Interview Notes, undated (Box 15)
      - Interview Transcripts
        - Crocker, Gary, 1987, undated (Box 15)
        - Feith, D., undated (Box 15)
        - Garrett (National Geographic ), undated (Box 15)
        - Head of Indian Delegation, 1989 (Box 15)
        - Leach, Jim, 1988 (Box 15)
        - Meselson, Matthew, undated (Box 15)
        - Robinson, Julian Perry, 1988, undated, (2 folders) (Box 15)
      - Introduction, circa 1990 (Box 15)
      - Research Files
        - 1967 (Box 15)
        - 1981-1989, undated, (7 folders) (Box 16)
        - Anthrax, 1979-1984 (Box 16)
        - Audiocassettes, 1981 1988, undated (21 tapes) (Box 24c)
        - Audiocassettes, 1988-1989, undated (10 tapes) (Box 24d)
        - Audiocassettes, undated, (6 tapes) (Box 24e)
        - Australian Reports, 1980-1985 (Box 16)
        - Bee Theory, 1980-1991, (3 folders) (Box 16)
        - Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention, circa 1980s (Box 16)
        - British Government Debates, 1985-1986 (Box 16)
        - Bush, George, 1989 (Box 16)
        - Chinese Papers, 1977-1989, (2 folders) (Box 16)
        - Clippings, 1989 (Box 16)
        - Concluding Section, 1980-1990, (2 folders) (Box 16)
        - Crocker, Gary, 1984-1988, undated (Box 16)
        - Haber, Fritz, circa 1988 (Box 16)
        - Hmong Refugees, 1984-1990 (Box 16)
        - Intelligence and Declassified Materials, 1981-1987, undated, (4 folders) (Box 16)
        - Israel, 1990 (Box 16)
        - Meselson, Matthew
          - 1970-1991, undated, (5 folders) (Box 16)
          - Foreign Policy, 1987 (Box 16)
        - Notebooks
          - 1979-1988, undated, (8 folders) (Box 16)
          - Meselson, Matthew, 1988, undated, (2 folders) (Box 17)
        - Notes
          - 1980-1988, undated, (9 folders) (Box 17)
          - Chronology, circa 1986, (2 folders) (Box 17)
          - End of Book, 1990 (Box 17)
          - Harris, Elisa, 1987, undated (Box 17)
          - Meselson, Matthew, 1980-1990, undated, (7 folders) (Box 17)
          - Meselson, Matthew--Interview, 1981 (Box 17)
          - Part II, undated (Box 17)
          - Robinson, Julian, 1990 (Box 17)
          - Sources, 1988, undated (Box 17)
          - Sverdlovsk, 1980-1988, undated, (5 folders) (Box 17)
          - Sverdlovsk--Chronology, 1979-1989 (Box 17)
          - Sverdlovsk/Hormats, Saul, 1988 (Box 17)
          - US Government Crusade on Yellow Rain, undated (Box 17)
          - US Government Leaks, undated (Box 17)
        - Nowicke, Joan, 1982-1989 (Box 17)
        - Outside Scientific Results--Mirocha, Chester and Watson, Sharon, 1982-1986, (2 folders) (Box 17)
        - Paris Conference, 1989, (2 folders) (Box 17)
        - Press Reports, 1981-1987 (Box 17)
        - Public Opinion, 1982 (Box 17)
        - Robinson, Julian Perry, 1985 (Box 17)
        - Scientific Papers, 1982, 1986 (Box 17)
        - Soviet Chemical Weapons, undated (Box 17)
        - Soviet Reactions, 1984-1990 (Box 17)
        - Soviet Reply to the United Nations, 1981-1982, undated (Box 17)
        - Sverdlovsk, 1966, 1980-1991, undated, (7 folders) (Box 18)
        - US Department of State Press Briefing, 1981-1988, (2 folders) (Box 18)
        - US Department of State, Reports to, 1985, undated, (3 folders) (Box 18)
        - Vietnam, 1968 (Box 18)
        - Zhang, Zhomgying, 1989 (Box 18)
      - Transcript, 1988-1990 (Box 18)
      - Typescript Part I, 1988-1990, undated, (6 folders) (Box 18)
      - Typescript/Draft Part I, 1988, undated, (2 folders) (Box 18)
      - Typescript Part II, 1990, undated, (6 folders) (Box 18)
  - Subseries I.2: Unpublished Articles, 1962-1995
    Subseries I.2: Unpublished Articles contains materials related to articles that Whiteside never published. There are three main topics covered in this subseries: French Caves, Joe Camel, and material about the Crytherian Phase. There is also a piece that Whiteside wrote on the arrival of the Beatles to the United States. Like subseries 1, this subseries consists of research articles and clippings, correspondence, drafts, and typescripts.
    - The Beatles--Draft, undated (Box 25)
    - French Caves
      - 3.5" disks, undated (Box 25)
      - "The Cave Under the Sea"--Typescript, undated, (3 folders) (Box 25)
      - Correspondence, 1992-1997 (Box 25)
      - Drafts, undated, (6 folders) (Box 25)
      - "The First Civilized Europeans"--Typescript, 1995 (Box 25)
      - Galleys, undated (Box 25)
      - Interview Transcripts--Clottes, Jean (partial), 1995, undated, (2 folders) (Box 25)
      - Photograph (unidentified), undated (Box 25)
      - Research Files
        - Audiocassettes, 1991-1992, undated (14 tapes) (Box 24f)
        - Notebooks, undated, (3 folders) (Box 25)
        - Notes
          - 1991-1993, undated, (16 folders) (Box 25)
          - Clottes, Jean, undated (Box 25)
          - Cosquer, Henri, 1992 (Box 25)
          - Courtin, Jean, 1992 (Box 25)
          - Enlene Visit, undated (Box 25)
      - Scientific Doubts, 1992 (Box 25)
      - Slides, undated (Box 25)
      - Travel Passes, 1987 (Box 25)
      - Trip to France--Logistics, 1992-1995 (Box 25)
      - Typescript (untitled), undated (Box 25)
    - Joe Camel
      - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 25)
      - Drafts, undated (Box 25)
      - Research Files
        - 1992 (inc. some correspondence) (Box 25)
        - Advertisements, undated (Box 25)
        - Cherner, Joe, 1992 undated (Box 25)
        - Clippings, 1964-1994, undated, (2 folders) (Box 25)
        - Council of Tobacco Research, 1992 (Box 25)
        - JAMA Reports, 1991 (Box 25)
        - Notebooks, 1976, 1992, undated, (2 folders) (Box 25)
        - Notes, circa 1990s (Box 25)
        - Philip Morris, 1987-1990 (Box 25)
        - RJ Reynolds
          - 1989 (Box 25)
          - Uptown Campaign, 1990 (Box 25)
        - Stickers and Posters, 1991, undated (Box 25)
        - Synar, Mike, 1988, 1992-1993, (2 folders) (Box 26)
        - Tobacco Industry Lobbying, 1992 (Box 26)
        - Tye, Joe, 1991, (2 folders) (Box 26)
      - Slides, undated (Box 26)
    - Television--Typescript (untitled), undated, (2 folders) (Box 26)
    - To the Crytherian Phase
      - Correspondence, 1963-1964, undated, (2 folders) (Box 26)
      - Drafts (partial), undated (Box 26)
      - Photographs, 1962 (Box 26)
      - Research Files--Notes, 1962, undated, (2 folders) (Box 26)
      - Typescript, undated, (4 folders) (Box 26)
      - Typescript (for submission to Houghton Mifflin Company), 1963, (2 folders) (Box 26)
    - Untitled Book on Advertising--Proposal, 1987 (Box 26)
  - Subseries I.3: General Reference Files, 1961-1987
    Series I.3: General Research Files contains research materials not associated directly to an article or book. There are several files related to a Dioxin Study Project that Whiteside took part in during the early 1980s as well as material on George Blake.
    - Advertisements--Endorsements by Celebrities, 1986, undated (Box 26)
    - Audiocassettes (unidentified), undated (10 tapes) (Box 24g)
    - Audiocassettes (unidentified), undated (7 tapes) (Box 24h)
    - Ban Sa Tong, Thailand, 1986 (Box 26)
    - BBC, 1985-1986 (Box 26)
    - Blake, George
      - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 26)
      - Research Files
        - 1961-1966, undated, (2 folders) (Box 26)
        - Aftermath, 1966, undated (Box 26)
        - Background, 1961, undated (Box 26)
        - Escape, 1966 (Box 26)
        - Escape Clues, 1966, undated (Box 26)
        - Notes, undated (Box 26)
        - Weigl, Benno, 1966, undated (Box 26)
    - Carbon Monoxide, 1972, (2 folders) (Box 26)
    - Chemical Warfare, 1982-1986, (2 folders) (Box 26)
    - Chemical Weapons--Audiocassettes, undated (9 tapes) (Box 24f)
    - Chemical Weapons--Audiocassettes, undated (3 tapes) (Box 24h)
    - Compact Discs, 1986 (Box 26)
    - Concerned Citizens of Montauk, 1979, undated (Box 26)
    - Dioxin Study Project
      - Agreement, 1980 (Box 26)
      - Correspondence, 1979-1984, (7 folders) (Box 26)
      - Report, 1980 (Box 26)
      - Research Files
        - 1986, undated, (2 folders) (Box 26)
        - Notebooks, 1980-1981, undated, (6 folders) (Box 27)
      - Twentieth Century Fund Proposal--Correspondence, 1981 (Box 27)
    - "Educational Television, Alternative Service Television and Pay-Television"--A Report Prepared for the Fund for the Republic, undated (Box 27)
    - Ford Foundation--Expenses, 1981 (Box 27)
    - Friendly, Fred, 1986 (Box 27)
    - Great Britain, 1986 (Box 27)
    - Money, 1986 (Box 27)
    - Notebooks, 1961, undated, (7 folders) (Box 27)
    - Privacy, 1986 (Box 27)
    - Reel-to-Reel Audio (unidentified), undated (3 reels) (Box 24)
    - Schwartz, Tony, 1984 (Box 27)
    - Stallone, Sylvester, 1985 (Box 27)
    - Stewart (Ullman), Natacha, 1986, undated (Box 27)
    - Television
      - Europe, 1986 (Box 27)
      - France, 1985-1986 (Box 27)
      - Japan, 1985 (Box 27)
      - News, 1987 (Box 27)
      - Soviet, undated (Box 27)
    - Trump, Donald, 1986 (Box 27)
    - Wortman, Albert, 1982-1984 (Box 27)
- Series II: Personal Papers, 1940-1995
  Series II: Personal Papers is a small series consisting in the main of correspondence from Whiteside's children. Represented here as well are letters to Whiteside over the course of his career which are unrelated to a specific article or book. This series also contains material related to the MacArthur Fellowship that Whiteside won in 1986. There is an undated school notebook containing notes and a Toronto Public Library card from 1940.
  - Correspondence
    - 1940s (Box 27)
    - 1950s (Box 27)
    - 1960s (Box 27)
    - 1970s (Box 27)
    - 1980s (Box 27)
    - 1990s (Box 27)
    - undated (Box 27)
    - Adams, Ted, 1977 (Box 27)
    - Cony, Ed (Wall St. Journal ), 1971 (Box 27)
    - Ford Foundation, 1973 (Box 27)
    - The New Yorker regarding the Newspaper Guild, 1976 (Box 27)
    - Shawn, William, 1969-1970, 1979 (Box 27)
    - Termination from The New Yorker, 1987 (Box 27)
    - Terrorism, 1977-1978 (Box 27)
    - Whiteside, Anne, 1972-1974 (Box 27)
    - Whiteside, Karen, 1968-1972 (Box 27)
    - Whiteside, Thomas to Marie Whiteside, 1974 (Box 27)
  - MacArthur Fellowship Montana Expedition, 1993 (Box 27)
  - MacArthur Foundation Fellowship, 1986 (Box 27)
  - The New Yorker
    - 1985-1986 (Box 27)
    - Articles Published in, 1977 1997, undated (Box 27)
    - Matching Gift Program, 1991 (Box 27)
    - New York Corporation Merger, 1985-1987 (Box 27)
    - Party Invitations, 1995 (Box 27)
  - Photographs and Negatives, undated (Box 27)
  - School Notebook, 1940 (Box 27)